A Guide to the Margaret B. Burruss Collection of Scott and Saufley Family Papers, 1786-1912 SC 0118
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Margaret B. Burruss Collection of Scott and Saufley Family Papers,
1786-1912, 1991
Special Collections, James Madison University
Scott, Reuben A., 1838-1912
Scott, Mary Catherine Saufley, 1833-1920
Scott family
Saufley family
SC 0118
1.10 cubic feet; 3 boxes
The Margaret B. Burruss Collection of Scott and Saufley Family Papers, 1786-1912, 1991, is comprised of correspondence, transcripts, photographs, and the Hanna family Bible.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated in July 1990 by Mrs. Margaret B. Burruss, a great-granddaughter of Reuben A. Scott and Mary (Mollie) Saufley Scott.
Bio/Historical Information
Rueben A. Scott and his fiancée, later wife, Mary (Mollie) Catherine Saufley, lived near Port Republic in Rockingham County, Virginia. She was slightly older than Reuben, and was well educated, having attended Fair View Academy and Miami Seminary in Missouri. Reuben Scott joined the Confederate forces as a private in the Company B, 10th Regiment, Virginia Infantry, at least by April 1861 when he was in his twenties. He suffered a wound to the arm at the Battle of Chancellorsville in May 1863. He was then taken prisoner of war at Port Republic in September 1864, and later paroled on May 23, 1865. He returned to live a prosperous life as a farmer in Port Republic, where he died in 1912.
Scope and Content
The Margaret B. Burruss Collection of Scott and Saufley Family Papers, 1789-1912, consists of three boxes containing letters, family records, photos, letter transcripts, and the Hanna family Bible. The collection relates to the Scott and Saufley families of Rockingham County, Virginia.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series:
Series 1: Scott-Saufley Correspondence, 1861-1865
Series 2: Family Letters, 1768-1912
Series 3: Miscellaneous, 1859-1861
Series 4: Photographs, ca. 1860s, 1912
Series 5: Envelopes, 1861-1912
Series 6: Transcripts, 1991
Index Terms
Subjects:
Scott, Reuben A., 1838-1912; Scott, Mary Catherine Saufley, 1833-1920; Scott, Reuben A., 1838-1912 -- Correspondence; Scott, Mary Catherine Saufley, 1833-1920 -- Correspondence; Scott family -- Correspondence; Saufley family -- Correspondence; Hanna family -- Sources; Whitmer family -- Correspondence; Ewing family -- Correspondence; Brown family -- Correspondence; Graham family -- Correspondence; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Infantry Regiment, 10th; Chancellorsville, Battle of, Chancellorsville, Va., 1863; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives; Virginia -- Social life and customs; Port Republic (Va.) -- History; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives, Confederate; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental histories
- Series 1: Scott-Saufley Correspondence, 1861-1865
  Scope and Content
  Series 1: Scott-Saufley Correspondence, 1861-1865, is comprised of six folders of Civil War correspondence between Reuben A. Scott and his wife Mary Catherine Saufley Scott (called Mollie). His letters describe camp life, preparation for battles, and his assignment of searching out and arresting deserters. Her letters describe events and news about family members and home. There are also several documents included that are relevant to the correspondence, such as the April 7, 1861 letter from Mollie's father giving her permission to marry, a leave of absence for Scott in Septmeber 1861, and copies of his muster rolls.
  - Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence, April 7, 1861-June 5, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence, June 8, 1861-July 20, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence, July 23, 1861-September 8, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence, September 26, 1861-December 23, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence, January 5, 1862-March 24, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence, April 12, 18662-May 23, 1865, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series 2: Family Letters, 1768-1912
  Series 2: Family Letters, 1786-1912, contains miscellaneous letters from members of the Whitmer, Ewing, Brown, Graham, as well as the Scott and Saufley family. Letter from both R.A. Scott and M.C. Saufley to various relatives are filed here. Also filed here are notes of debts and R.A. Scott's obituary and will.
  - Family letters, 1786-1857 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family letters, 1858-1861 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Family letters, 1861-1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series 3: Miscellaneous, 1859-1861
  Series 3: Miscellaneous, 1859-1861, contains M.C. Saufley's daybook and pamphlet, The Soldier's Mission in the Crisis of 1861 that contains a note by R. A. Scott ("found on battlefield"). This folder also holds several clippings that were photocopied onto preservation paper for placement with the letters they accompanied. The Hanna Family Bible also forms part of this series and includes two pages of genealogical data.
  - Miscellaneous, 1859-1861 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hanna family Bible, undated (Box OV 1)
- Series 4: Photographs, ca. 1860s, 1912
  Series 4: Photographs, ca. 1860s, 1912, consists of three cases photos of R.A. Scott, one cased photo of Mollie Scott identified and dated by the donor as 1861, and one mounted photo of R. A. Scott in his casket.
  - Photographs, ca. 1860s, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series 5: Envelopes, 1861-1912
  Series 5: Envelopes, 1861-1912, correspond to the letters in Series 1 and Series 2. They were separated from their letters during an initial processing campaign. The separated envelopes have penciled notations on them referring back to their original letter.
  - Envelopes, 1861-1912 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series 6: Transcripts, 1991
  Series 6: Transcripts, undated, is comprised of typed transcripts of all correspondence located in Series 1 and Series 2.
  - Transcripts to Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence dated April 7, 1861-June 5, 1861, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Transcripts to Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence dated June 8, 1861-July 20, 1861, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Transcripts to Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence dated July 23, 1861-September 8, 1861, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Transcripts to Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence dated September 26, 1861-December 23, 1861, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Transcripts to Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence dated January 5, 1862-March 24, 1862, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Transcripts to Reuben A. Scott/Mollie Catherine Saufley Scott correspondence dated April 12, 18662-May 23, 1865, undated, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Transcripts to Family letters dated 1786-1857, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Transcripts to Family letters dated 1858-1861, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Transcripts to Family letters dated 1861-1912, undated, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)